Guide to the Records of the Peace Corps Training Program RISM.RG.6
New York University Archives
Records of the Jamaica Peace Corps Training Program
1961-1982
1962
New York University Archives
Rubin, Vera D.
RISM.RG.6
22 boxes
In 1961 the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) was contracted to train volunteers for the United States Peace Corps. Transferred to the Caribbean, the volunteers assisted the Jamaican government by training workers in librarianship, industrial arts, nursing and vocational education. The collection, which reflects the early years of the Peace Corps, and RISM's specialized knowledge of the Caribbean, includes correspondence, financial records, teaching papers, training guides, clippings, photographs, print material, reports, cassette tapes, and compact discs.
Provenance
The records of the Peace Corps Training Program were generated by Dr. Vera D. Rubin (1911 - 1985), Director of the Research Institute for The Study of Man (RISM) and her staff in fulfillment of a contract with The U.S. Peace Corps.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research with the exception of part or all of Series III, IV, V, and IX, which are restricted.
Historical Note
On March 1, 1961, President John F. Kennedy established the U.S. Peace Corps to promote international peace efforts through volunteer workers. Based on its specialization in Caribbean research, the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) was selected to train Peace Corps volunteers to assist and support the vocational adult education programs sponsored by the government in Jamaica, West Indies.
The initial phase of the training program was conducted between April 2 - May 31, 1962 with Peace Corps volunteers housed at the International House situated on the Columbia University campus. Dr. Vera Rubin served as a consultant for the program, which was co-directed by Drs. Lambros Comitas and Robert Stigler. Course work included Caribbean (area) studies, American studies and world affairs, technical and agricultural training, commerce, industrial arts and health care. Noted anthropologists Sidney Mintz, David Lowenthal, M.G. Smith and others gave lectures. Many individuals involved in public service provided lectures for the American Affairs unit, notably Dean Acheson, U.S. Secretary of State from 1949 - 1953, Zbigniew K. Brzezinski, and Adlai E. Stevenson.
The Program's field trips and extra-curricular activities included a visit to Hyde Park, New York, where volunteers spoke with Mrs. Eleanor Roosevelt, attending the birthday party of President John F. Kennedy at Madison Square Garden in New York City and visits to the Library of Congress in Washington, D.C.
During the second phase of the training program, volunteers received additional instruction and orientation to the region at the University College of the West Indies (UCWI) at Mona, Jamaica, W.I. Approximately 30 Peace Corps volunteers were assigned to diverse institutions, including youth camps at Chestervald and Cobbla, Regional Trade Training Centers, Teacher Training Colleges that included the Mico Training College for Teachers, the Shortwood Training College for Women Teachers, and at Frome Senior High Schools, Holmwood Technical School in Manchester, Vere Technical School in Clarendon and technical institutes in Port Antonio and Montego Bay. Their work responsibilities included teaching industrial arts, vocational skills, commercial bookeeping, chemistry, biology and physics. Other volunteers worked as nurse-educators, participated in agricultural projects or assisted the Jamaican Library Service, and the University College of the West Indies with cataloguing and classification.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Jamaica Peace Corps Training Program document the activities of the U.S. Peace Corps, and the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) from the 1960s through the 1980s. The bulk of the collection, which consists of 21 boxes and approximately 12 linear feet, documents the actual training program, which was conducted between April - May 1962. The materials generated during the course of the Program are mainly textual in nature comprising correspondence between the U.S. Peace Corps, staff and faculty members, and Dr. Vera Rubin. Other textual documents include program guides, which outline the goals and objectives of setting up a training program and includes RISM's own training proposal. Syllabai and teaching papers, publications, clippings, maps, reports and print materials associated with the Program's graduation ceremony are also included.
Other formats in the collection are individual and group photographs of the Peace Corps Volunteers, and tickets from the birthday celebrtion organized for John F. Kennedy at Madison Square Garden. Audiovisual materials include a film reel of the volunteer's visit to Mrs. Eleanor Roosevelt, audiocassettes and reel-to-reel tapes of the Jamaican Language Guide by Mrs. Beryl Bailey, class lectures, and the Graduation ceremony. Note: Several series pertaining to the Peace Corps volnteers are restricted due to the sensitive nature of the materials and privacy of individuals. These series are as follows: Series III. Volunteer Registration Records, Series IV. Health Services, Series V. Volunteer Evaluation, and Series IX. Volunteer Files.
Arrangement
The papers of the Jamaica Peace Corps. Project are arranged as # series, and some further arranged as subseries. The contents of each series or subseries is arranged chronologically with the exception of Series V, Volunteer Records, which is arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 19 series:
Series
I. Correspondence
II. Peace Corps Program Development
III. Volunteer Registration Records [Restricted]
IV. Program Health Services [Restricted]
V. Volunteer Evaluation Records [Restricted]
VI. Program Administration Records
VII. Teaching Papers
VIII. Field Trips and Extra-Curricular Activities
IX. Volunteer Files [Restricted]
X. Regional Placement Records
XI. Photographs
XII. Public Relations
XIII. Clippings
XIV. Audiovisual Materials
XV. Maps
XVI. Peace Corps Graduation Ceremony
XVII. Peace Corps Volunteer Publications
XVIII. Final Reports
XIX. Miscellaneous Papers
Related Material
The Vera Rubin Papers, RG 1 (at RISM)
At NYU:
Study of the Aspirations of Youth in a Developing Country (The Trinidad Study), RISM RG 5
Attitudes of Medical Students, RISM RG 7
Inter-University Consortium, RISM RG 9
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Correspondence.; Financial records; Publications (documents); Pamphlets.; American history and culture.; New York (N.Y.).; Telegrams; Articles.; Manuscripts; Form letters.; Reports.; CD-ROMs.; Vocational Guidance |z Jamaica.; Hyde Park |z Dutchess County |z N.Y.; Maps.; Printed ephemera.; Drafts (documents); Certificates.; Audiovisual materials.; Invitations.; Washington (D.C.); Jamaica.; Communism.; Anthropology.; Photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Geography.; Postcards.; Shriver, Sargent, 1915-2011; Manley, Michael, 1924-1997; Roosevelt, Anna Eleanor; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Columbia University. International House; Columbia University. Anthropology Dept. Faculty; Brzezinski, Zbigniew, 1928-; McBurnie, Beryl, 1913-2000; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1835-1914; United Nations; Smith, M. G. (Michael Garfield); Wright, Herbert; Comitas, Lambros; University College of the West Indies (Mona, Jamaica); Peace Corps (U.S.); Research Institute for the Study of Man
- Series I. Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  1.0 linear feet (2 boxes) arranged chronologically. The correspondence series, which contains incoming and outgoing letters, documents the early relationship between the U.S. Peace Corps and the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM). The bulk of material was generated between March - April of 1962, and relates specifically to the training curriculum for Peace Corps Volunteers (PCV). Notable correspondents include Seargent Shriver, director of the Peace Corps, the Honorable Norman W. Manley, Beryl Bailey, H.D. Huggins and other faculty members of the University College of the West Indies (UCWI). Letters establishing potential placement, recruitment of training personnel and forms letters to new volunteers are also included.
  - Correspondence, 1961 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, draft program timetable, 1962 February (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, notes, 1962 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, telegram, notes, 1962 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Peace Corps Volunteer lists, welcome letters, 1962 March (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1962 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1962 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, notes, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, telegrams, notes, ephemera, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1962 May (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1962 May (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1962 May, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1962 June (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, notes, 1962 June, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1962 July (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, concert flyer, 1962 August (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, list of telegrams and cables, 1962 November, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series II. Peace Corps Program Development
  1.25 linear feet (2.5 boxes) arranged chronologically. This series contains national and international Peace Corps programs that provide an overview of the goals and principles of the agency. Other materials include the Peace Corps Fact Book, instructional handbooks, syllabi, training reports, testing requirements, project descriptions, and related correspondence and memorandum, which were used in the development of RISM's training program (see Series VI).
  - Handbook for Foreign Student Advisers, Part VI. Miscellaneous Government Regulations Affecting Alien Students in the United States, 1960 June (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Care-Peace Corps Community Development Project for Colombia, 1961 - 1963, 1961 June (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Peace Corps Training Program, Ghana Project, University of California at Berkeley; miscellaneous papers, 1961 July, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Instructional Situations, 1961 August (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Instructional Situations, 1961 August (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Wanted--3,000 Teachers by Sargent Shriver, Director, The Peace Corps, Volunteer Policies, 1961 October (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General Principles Underlying the Training Program, 1961 October (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Peace Corps program requirements [abstract], 1961 November (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Peace Corps Training Program, Teachers for Sierra Leone, 6 November to 22 December 1961, Teachers College, Columbia University, 1961 November (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Peace Corps Fact Book, brochures, 1961 November (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Warner-Griscom memorandum on volunteerism in Jamaica, W.I., 1961 December (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Tanganyika Training Program Area Studies [mimeograph], 1961 November (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Description of Peace Corps Placement Test, instructor opportunities, volunteer profiles, programs in progress, 1961 November-December (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Warner-Griscom Jamaica, W.I. Training Report [typescript], 1962 January (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Warner-Griscom Jamaica, W.I. Training Report [typescript], 1962 January (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Peace Corps Training Program, Brazil/4H Project Syllabus, 1962 January (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - New Mexico State University, Peace Corps Training Program, 1962 February (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Training Program Syllabus, Peace Corps - Colombia II. Project, 1962 February (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Jamaica Peace Corps Project Description, 1962 February (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Peace Corps Training Program: A Guide to Its Basic Components, 1962 February (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Biographies of Peace Corps Trainees, Colombia II Project, Arizona University, 1962 February (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New York University Somalia Peace Corps Project, 1962 March-April (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - New York University Somalia Peace Corps Project, 1962 March-April (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Syllabus Peace Corps Chile-Venezuela Training Project, Brattleboro, Vermont, 1962 April (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Warner-Griscom Jamaica, W.I. Training Report (revised), 1962 April (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Koinonia Magazine, 1962 April-May (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Brazil II Project - Sao Francisco Valley, Peace Corps Training Program, 1962 July (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Brazil II Project - Peace Corps Trainees, 1962 July (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Brazil II Project - Curriculum, 1962 July (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - TVA Training Schedule for the Brazil II Project - Sao Francisco Valley, Peace Corps Training Program, 1962 September (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series III. Volunteer Registration Records [Some material restricted]
  .5 linear feet (1 box), arranged chronologically. This series documents the registration process and includes correspondence, questionnaires, volunteer lists, Peace Corps brochures, instructions, forms, and print material from International House where volunteers resided during their training. Because of the sensitive nature of material that appears on the registration forms, folders 13 and 14 are restricted.
  - Peace Corps Background Information Form, 1961 June (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Personal Interview Records [blank], 1961 August (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Instructions for Completing Form PC-52 Notice of Volunteers Registered for Training, 1961 September (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Personal History Blanks, 1961 September (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report, forms for International House, notes, 1961 November (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Project Invitation Summary Sheets, correspondence with Peace Corps questionnaire, 1962 February-March (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - The Peace Corps Fact Book, forms, instructions, 1962 March (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Registration Data Sheets A - K, 1962 March (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Registration Data Sheets L - Z, 1962 March (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Jamaica Instructions for Reporting to the Peace Corps Reception Center, International House, New York, 1962 March (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - U.S. Civil Service Commission Fingerprint Charts, volunteer identification card numbers, 1962 March (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - International House brochures, room assignments, instructions, memorandum, notes, 1962 March-April (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Program Health Services [RESTRICTED]
  approximately .5 linear feet (1 box), arranged chronologically. The papers in this series, which relate to the health and well being of Peace Corps volunteers, include brochures, medical budgets, correspondence, medical reports and summaries. Because of the sensitive nature of the material, the entire series is restricted.
- Series V. Volunteer Evaluation Forms [RESTRICTED]
  .5 liner feet (1 box), arranged chronologically. This series mainly consists of personal interviews, psychiatric evaluations, and self-evaluation forms for volunteers. Correspondence, articles, reports, statistical summary cards and notes are also included. Because of the sensitive nature of the papers, the entire series is restricted.
- Series VI. Program Administration Records
  .5 linear feet (1 box), arranged chronologically. The papers in this series document the organization and day-to-day operations of the Jamaica Peace Corps Training Program. Included are program proposals, curriculum vitae for staff and faculty, program schedules, syllabi, correspondence, general reading lists, and notes (see Series VII. Teaching Papers for specific subject curriculum).
  - Proposal for a Peace Corps Training Program, Contract Article I - Definitions, Article II - General Scope of the Program, draft chart, notes, 1961 December (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Proposal for a Peace Corps Training Program [original typescript], 1961 December (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - List of Program staff and faculty, 1962 February-March (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Curriculum vitae for staff and faculty, A - B, 1962 February-March (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Curriculum vitae for staff and faculty, C, 1962 February-March (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Curriculum vitae for staff and faculty, D - L, 1962 February-March (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Curriculum vitae for staff and faculty, O - S, 1962 February-March (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Curriculum vitae for Mottram Torres, 1962 February-March (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, curriculum vitae for staff and faculty U - Z, staff and faculty telephone address list, notes, 1962 February-March (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Draft progam charts, notes, 1962 March (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Draft daily schedules [draft], notes, 1962 March (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Final daily schedules, 1962 March (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Notes, 1962 March-May (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Series VII. Teaching Papers
  Two linear feet (4 boxes), arranged chronologically. This series highlights the academic and technical training taught in the program. These training materials have been organized as five subseries: Subseries A. Peace Corps Orientation, Program Syllabi, and Area Studies, on the history, geography and culture of Jamaica, W.I., including the original typescript, A Language Guide to Jamaica, written by Beryl Bailey. Note: Recorded versions of this guide can be found in Series XIV, Audio-visual Materials. The papers in Subseries B. Technical Studies, relate to studies in the industrial arts, vocational education, biological science, agriculture, library science, nursing, plumbing, auto mechanics and other trades. Subseries C. American Studies and World Affairs focused on communism and other newsworthy events during the 1960s. The papers in Subseries D. Health Training, mainly relate to public health education. Subseries E. Physical Education relates to physical fitness soccer, cricket and other sports activities.
  - Subseries A. Peace Corps Orientation
    - Lists of instructors, books and articles, 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Notes on the Language of Communism, published by the Division on Training, Peace Corps, Washington, D.C., 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Notes on the Language of Communism, notes, 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - The Power of the Democratic Idea, Special Studies Project Report VI, Rockefeller Brothers Fund, America at Mid-Century Series [1960], 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1962 June (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Peace Corps Orientation Course, Institute of Social and Economic Research (ISER), University of the West Indies, Jamaica, W.I., 1962 June (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Syllabi, Jamaica Peace Corps Training Program [1st ed.], 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Syllabi, Jamaica Peace Corps Training Program, 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Syllabi, Jamaica Peace Corps Training Program, 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Syllabi, Jamaica Peace Corps Training Program, 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Syllabi, Jamaica Peace Corps Training Program, 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Scientific Advisory Committee for Jamaica, 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Lists of guest lecturers, educational materials from the N.Y. Board of Education, and other resources circulated to Peace Corps Volunteers, 1962 April-May (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Language Guide to Jamaica [original typescript], 1962 February (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Language Guide to Jamaica [draft], 1962 February (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Language Guide to Jamaica [draft material, partial copies], 1962 February (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Language Guide to Jamaica [autographed], 1962 February (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, course description, notes, 1962 March (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Background to Jamaica, West Indies, 1962 March (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Reading list, articles, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Reading lists, reprint articles, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Reading lists, reprint articles, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Reading lists, reprint articles, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Reading lists, reprint articles, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - List of materials submitted by University College of the West Indies (UCWI), pamphlets, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - A Warm Welcome from America to a New Neighbor, the University College of the West Indies, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - University College of the West Indies Calendar 1961 - 62, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - International visitors list, published by the Department of State, Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Short Bibliography of Recent Literature on Jamaica, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Questionnaire, essays, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Questionnaire, test booklets, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Test booklets, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Test booklets, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Test booklets, 1962 April (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1962 May-June (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Subseries B. Technical Training
    - Course schedules, notes, 1962 March-April (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Recruitment material for Jamaica Agricultural Project; trainee questions for School of Agriculture, Jamaica, W.I., 1962 March-April (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence related to vocational training, notes, 1962 April (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - List of materials for agricultural training, article distribution list, course schedule for agriculture and biological science, notes, 1962 April (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Articles related to technical projects, 1962 April (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - A Report on Labour Supply in Rural Jamaica, 1962 April (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Memorandum and course assignments for agricultural students, student paper, 1962 April (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Bookkeeping training schedule, publication orders, 1962 April (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, proposed course outline, schedule for industrial arts training, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Instructions for industrial training, book orders for industrial arts, vocational training, notes, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Apprentices Teachers Guide[1952], 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Trade Analysis Index for Automotive Field, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Instructions for industrial teacher training; auto mechanic assignment sheets, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Orientation program for librarians, training curriculum, schedule, notes, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - The Jamaica Library Service Annual Report, [1959 - 1960], 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Jamaica Library Service Background History, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Audio-visual aids program correspondence, schedule, preliminary course outline, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Subseries C. American Studies and World Affairs
    - Course outline for Public Law and Government [draft], correspondence, outline, 1962 March-April (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, biographical essay for Herbert L. Wright, Youth Secretary, NAACP See also Series X for photograph, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Revised course outlines, draft material, notes, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Lists of articles and books, notes, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Reading assignments and examinations, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1962 April-May (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Grades for first exam, 1962 May (Box 9, Folder 24)